Come on, let's go! Let's move forward together towards final victory!
A new atomic bomb, every 6 weeks.
Gone are the days when our enemies could threaten us with nuclear weapons.
Saying I've got the H-bomb means I now have the capacity to wreak mass
destruction on an opposing country.
There's only one person in the world today who's more unpredictable than Kim
Jong-un, and that's Donald Trump.
North Korea had better stop making threats against the United States,
or face fire and fury.
As a child, I thought Americans were wolves, animals that take on the appearance
of human beings.
Kim Jong-un is the spitting image of his grandfather.
He's strong-willed, determined and has a big ego.
The Italian Mafia has never reached the level of sophistication,
size and global reach of North Korean organized crime.
We don't know what to do with North Korea, we've tried everything.
The moment of truth is approaching.
We are in Vienna, at the United Nations nuclear monitoring center.
That night, the experts are awakened by a seismic alert.
Our monitoring system has been put on alert by a seismic event on the Korean peninsula.
We have automatic processing that tells us immediately whether it's an
earthquake or whether there's a possibility of an explosion.
We know immediately, from the shape of the signal, that it's not an earthquake
but a nuclear test.
The coordinates point to this mountainous area in North Korea.
The country has already tested 5 atomic bombs on this site over the last ten years.
It's the only country still conducting nuclear tests, since all the others have
stopped 20 years ago.
And North Korea makes no secret of the fact.
Quite the contrary, in fact.
A few hours after the explosion, state television interrupted its programs for
an official announcement.
North Korea's nuclear engineers have successfully tested an H-bomb for
intercontinental missiles at our test site,
an H-bomb designed for intercontinental missiles.
This is in line with the Workers' Party of Korea's plan to build a strategic
nuclear force.
North Korean leader Kim Jong-un is delighted.
He has just tested an H-bomb, 16 times more powerful than the Hiroshima bomb.
To say "I've got the H-bomb",
means I now have the capacity to inflict mass destruction on an opposing country.
The second thing is to say that I have the capacity to do something that
that, until now, only the big countries have been able to do.
This is very advanced technology.
If you have it, you're in the Club.
If you don't, you're despised.
Kim Jong-un is now awaiting reactions from the international community.
North Korea's nuclear test seriously violated international rules. China is
firmly opposed to it.
We will be discussing the strengthening of European sanctions against North
Korea. This is a matter of urgency.
Military action is certainly an option. Is it inevitable? Nothing is inevitable.
I hope we won't have to resort to military action against North Korea.
That would be a very sad day for North Korea.
The North Korean leader is on the radar of the great powers.
And that's what he was hoping for.
To be taken seriously, particularly by the United States.
What the North Koreans want is for the United States to feel threatened.
And they're going the extra mile, giving the outside world - and especially the
Americans - the impression that they're crazy,
that they're crazy.
At 33, Kim Jong-un is the unbridled leader of North Korea's totalitarian regime.
A few months earlier, he was commemorating the 105th birthday of his grandfather,
the late Kim Il-sung, founder of the regime in 1948.
It was he who launched North Korea into the nuclear race in the 1960s.
So it's his grandson who is at the heart of all concerns.
One wonders if he really has a good head on his shoulders.
He's very emotional, even angry.
He sometimes puts his ego before reason.
That's why he's perhaps more dangerous than his father or grandfather.
Kim Jong-un is uncontrollable.
He wants to show the world his power.
That's a risk for every country.
Kim Jong-un likes to stage these threats.
The day after the military parade, he organizes a grand spectacle in praise of
the army.
This was Nixon's strategy.
If the Russians thought the Americans were crazy, they'd be more careful.
That's what the North Koreans are doing, only much more muscular.
The North Korean leader even went so far as to reproduce in computer-generated
images the explosion of a nuclear missile on an American city.
The message has never been so explicit, and no one knows how seriously to take it.
North Korea is a huge black hole for American intelligence.
The regime's decisions are often indecipherable.
The absence of real-time information on the North Korean leader's strategic
intentions is a huge problem for us.
It's a situation that no American president has ever had to face before.
Faced with Kim Jong-un's nuclear provocations, the international community seems paralyzed.
But how could such a small country, cut off from the rest of the world, acquire
nuclear weapons?
To understand this, we need to go back 70 years, to the time when the North
Korean dictatorship was founded.
As you will see, Kim Jong-un is merely the heir to a system.
It all began in 1948, during the Second World War. Americans and Soviets
liberated Korea from the Japanese.
They now wanted to share the running of the country.
The South for the Americans and the North for the Soviets.
With an arbitrary border dividing the peninsula in two, the 38th parallel.
In North Korea, Stalin was looking for a leader who could defend Soviet interests.
And he thought he had found the ideal candidate.
A certain Kim Il-sung.
In September 1948, the first legislative elections were held in the new People's
Republic of Korea.
On that day, a man came to power.
The new Prime Minister, a certain Kim Il-sung. He was barely 36.
A very young man.
A big surprise in a still very traditional country where age is everything.
Many wondered.
Is it really possible to have such a young leader?
The country's other communist leaders don't really respect him.
Because he lacked diplomatic and political experience.
Yet it was he who Stalin sought to install in power in North Korea.
For he had long proved his bravery and loyalty to Soviet power.
He had been part of a Soviet military unit for several years on Russian soil.
His children had been born in the USSR.
The Russians knew him well and trusted him.
Stalin preferred someone young who could be manipulated.
He was convinced that he would be able to manipulate Kim Il-sung perfectly and
that, all in all, he would be a sort of Soviet Union sub-prefect in North Korea.
But Stalin was wrong.
Kim Il-sung was not the puppet he thought he had put in power.
On the contrary, he was a man of great ambition.
With the Russians, Kim Il-sung is very subtle, very respectful. He's the perfect
pupil and he plays, I'd say, low profile for two or three years.
But he wants power, he wants absolute power where he is and he wants power
throughout the peninsula to establish his domination once and for all.
Kim Il-sung has a secret dream: to reign over a reunified Korea.
But for this, he needs Soviet support.
In March 1950, Kim Il-sung made an official visit to Moscow.
Stalin invited him to dine face-to-face in his dacha.
Kim Il-sung took advantage of the occasion to reveal his plans.
His dream is to destabilize the South so that the regime collapses.
So the only solution is war, i.e. to invade the South, which he is convinced
will collapse like a house of cards.
What Kim Il-sung wants is logistical help, buying weapons if necessary,
financial support too, and then political backing.
The Korean leader was convincing, but Stalin hesitated.
Attacking South Korea also meant attacking the United States.
In the midst of the Cold War, this was taking far too many risks.
What Stalin wanted to be sure of was that there would be no strategic, i.e.
nuclear, shift. Basically, why not have a traditional war?
It should not degenerate into block-to-block confrontations with atomic weapons.
That's what's not possible.
Stalin remained cautious. He agreed to help Kim Il-sung conquer the South,
but he would only supply equipment. No Soviet soldiers would reinforce the North
Korean troops.
Three months later, 200,000 North Korean troops crossed the 38th parallel.
They invaded South Korea. The offensive was dazzling, but it was stopped dead in
its tracks.
What Kim Il-sung didn't understand at all was that Korea was the United States'
protégé at the United Nations.
They had a commitment to South Korea, not a security treaty, but at least a
political commitment.
The United States quickly realized that this war was more than just a local war
and became, it must be said, a war between the 2 blocs.
From the outset of the offensive, the American army was at the side of the South
Korean forces.
Kim Il-sung's troops were no match for the striking power of the US Air Force.
The Americans pushed them back and even entered North Korea.
Kim Il-sung was not prepared for war with the Americans. When the US Air Force
entered the scene, he didn't stand a chance.
But the North Korean leader still has a card to play.
His powerful neighbor China did not appreciate this intrusion by the American army.
China then entered the conflict.
The Chinese intervened when the Americans were getting very close to their border.
Hundreds of thousands of Chinese volunteers, in fact disguised soldiers,
gradually pushed the Americans back.
The Chinese intervention triggered panic in Washington, which stepped up its strikes.
A deluge of fire rains down on North Korea.
The destruction in North Korea was appalling.
Civilians and entire villages were destroyed by the tons of napalm poured in by
the American army.
In Korea, the Americans used the same massive bombing strategy as in the Second
World War.
They bombed everything they could.
This caused deep psychological trauma.
At the end of the three-year war, North Korea was devastated.
Three million dead, a border that had not moved and no peace treaty signed.
Kim Il-sung's attempted invasion failed.
On the face of it, one might consider that Kim Il-sung had lost.
But not at all. For him, it's not a war that's over, it's a war that's going on.
For the moment, it's a truce. But I'm going on. And one day, I'm going to win.
For his dreams of greatness are still alive.
Unable to reign over a reunified Korea, he laid the foundations for a
dictatorship in a devastated North Korea.
This defeat was to become his strength.
Thanks to the Korean War, he took absolute power. That was Kim Il-sung's victory.
From Pyongyang in the late 50s, the nationalist leader established totalitarian power.
The entire country was in a permanent state of mobilization. And paranoia set in.
All opponents who could overshadow the regime had to be eliminated.
The party embarks on an extraordinarily violent purge of all those under suspicion.
And it almost becomes a state law. It is estimated that nearly half a million
people disappeared.
To assert absolute power, Kim Il-sung created a military state.
He set up several political police forces and brought the army to the forefront.
At the same time, a powerful propaganda machine was set up. The war had
generated fears. The regime was going to exploit them.
The Americans who had ravaged the country were presented to the people as the
worst enemies.
We've been taught this hatred since we were children.
From childhood, North Koreans are taught that Americans are invaders.
They are described in textbooks as barbarians who massacre innocent civilians.
As a child, I thought the Americans were wolves, animals who take on the
appearance of human beings.
But the war nourished other resentments. Kim Il-sung has not forgotten the lack
of Soviet support.
On the surface, Kim Il-sung assures the Soviets that he is still a good friend.
But behind the scenes, he is doing everything to increase his independence.
To distance himself from Moscow, he invented a new form of communism in Korean
colors: juche.
The term juche simply means to be independent, to have a kind of character that
allows you to go it alone.
So it's a term linked to this idea of the Korean nation independent of the rest
of the world.
One day, in a meeting, he explained this to the party members.
The pro-Soviets want us to copy the Soviet model, the pro-Chinese want to
imitate China.
No, we have to build our revolution and our country in our own way.
An autonomous and emancipated North Korea: an ambitious program.
But the dictator still needs his Soviet allies.
Since the war, the American army has left tens of thousands of soldiers on its
bases in South Korea.
Washington increased its deterrent presence by deploying short-range missiles
equipped with nuclear warheads.
By 1965, there were almost 750 warheads in South Korea, all aimed at the North.
The Americans installed everything they needed to guard against any real
invasion attempt from the North.
The Americans considered and officially announced that South Korea was protected
by the American nuclear umbrella.
We clearly threatened to use nuclear weapons during the Korean War.
So it's not a theoretical threat in the minds of the North Koreans.
At least two American presidents have threatened them with a nuclear bomb,
although none of them actually carried it out.
Kim Il-sung seized the opportunity to ask Moscow for the same protection.
Kim Il-sung asked the Soviet Union to supply North Korea with missiles of
comparable range and quality, but the Russians refused.
Obviously, they were afraid of providing him with sophisticated weapons that
they might use in the wrong way and for the wrong reasons.
Once again, the Soviets disappointed the North Korean dictator.
Kim Il-sung made atomic weapons his obsession.
And since no one was willing to provide it, he tried to build it himself.
Naturally, he was angry at his Soviet allies for refusing to help him with his project.
So, using North Korean resources, he set out to develop an autonomous program.
When Kim Il-sung began designing this program in the 60s, he believed that the
next war would be a nuclear one.
So he ordered all military bases moved underground.
But his country had no nuclear experience.
To make up for this, Kim Il-sung once again approached Moscow.
He wants to obtain a civil nuclear reactor, the kind used to produce electricity.
He won't be able to build his own bomb, but at least he'll have access to the technology.
The Soviets choose to give them a tiny research reactor as a gesture of generosity.
But it's very useful for the North Koreans, as they can start to learn the
science of the atom.
The reactor was designed for research and for exclusively peaceful use.
In 1965, North Korea began its nuclear program in complete secrecy.
But Kim Il-sung already knew that he would never see it through to the end.
At the age of 58, the all-powerful dictator was worried about a tumor that had
appeared in his neck.
To ensure the continuity of his nuclear project, he must start preparing his succession.
For Kim Il-sung, the problem is how to ensure the continuity of his regime.
From the outset, he had considered a monarchical solution.
The only solution was to have a leader who, like his predecessor, would maintain
and even increase his power.
To avoid an internal war that would weaken the regime, the patriarch came up
with an idea unheard of in the Communist world.
Pyongyang has become a backyard, with everyone dreaming of power.
Anyone can take it, as long as they succeed.
So when all allies are potential dangers, when anyone can betray him,
he can only find someone in his family.
Kim Il-sung has always been very loyal to his family.
Unlike other communist leaders, he trusts only his family.
Kim Il-sung has three sons. One of them will be entrusted with the reins of the country.
Logic would dictate that it should be the eldest, Kim Jong-il. But the patriarch
has trouble seeing him as his successor.
Unlike his father, who is glorious, good-looking and always in a suit,
in fact, he's always in boiler suits,
he's short, poorly dressed.
Kim Il-sung finds him ugly, he doesn't like him very much, he finds him too
flattering, sycophantic.
He doesn't trust him completely, he's suspicious of him.
The old dictator especially disapproves of his eldest son's antics.
It's all the palace talks about.
They were drunken evenings with lots of very naked young women.
A typical life of a prince, of an absolute monarchy.
But at 28, Kim Jong-il dreams of succeeding his father.
So he's going to do everything in his power to earn his father's trust.
Kim Jong-il is always behind his father. He even ties his shoes, washes his
feet, serves him food and cuts his meat.
And the Koreans think that's great.
It's become his trademark, in a way, to be in his father's shadow so that it
affects his father.
And his strategy doesn't stop there.
Kim Jong-il is already working within the party.
He's in charge of propaganda.
He's going to set up a cult in his father's honor to flatter his ego.
The Department of Propaganda and Agitation is one of the most powerful
departments, in charge of managing the leader's image.
Kim Jong-il's father worship is hysterical.
Statues are everywhere. There are, it seems, 30,000 statues of him all over the country.
An infinite cult of personality.
Everything is renamed Kim Il-sung. The country became Kim Il-sung country.
We learn about Kim Il-sung's childhood in elementary school, his adolescence in
junior high and high school.
We grow up with his revolutionary past. When you finish school, that's the end
of the indoctrination.
At that point, we no longer think of him as a human being, but as a god.
The first sentence I learned to write was "Thank you father Kim Il-sung".
After that, I learned to write my name and my parents' names.
And it was the same for everyone.
Everyone in North Korea thought Kim Il-sung was a god who lived above mankind.
If you call Kim Il-sung by his proper name, you must die.
Always add a qualifier in front of his name, such as "glorious leader". If you
just say his name, you're considered a political criminal.
Four years later, Kim Jong-il's plan has borne fruit.
His father, who had survived the mood, had just chosen him as his successor.
From February 1974 onwards, the media started talking about Kim Jong-il as the
party leader.
This meant that he was the successor.
But nothing was known about him.
Kim Il-sung would remain at the head of the country until his death, but he
entrusted internal affairs to his son.
At the age of 32, Kim Jong-il had to demonstrate his ability to ensure the
continuity of the regime.
That year, the North Korean economy was hit hard by the oil crisis.
And it was up to him to find a solution.
Within six months, North Korea was almost bankrupt.
It could no longer repay its loans, it was running out of cash, and banks were
no longer willing to lend.
At the same time, Kim Jong-il realized that if he ever wanted to take the reins
of power, the regime had to survive.
Otherwise, there's no future for him and his family.
He realizes that it's essential to raise cash at a time when the whole economy
is on the verge of imploding.
To boost the coffers, Kim Jong-il decides to create a secret administration,
Bureau 39.
Its mission was to find money, wherever it came from.
They use the expression "catching dollars in the air".
This meant exploiting every possible avenue to find hard currency.
Bureau 39 controlled all exports,
such as industrial production, freight forwarding and even gold bullion production.
They ran all North Korea's most lucrative businesses.
And the most lucrative business for Kim Jong-il was international drug trafficking.
They were very creative. They got into organized crime on a massive scale.
It's very interesting, and it mainly involved the production and distribution of
hard drugs around the world.
The North Koreans do business without asking too many questions about what is
legal and what is not.
For them, everything is legal.
On Kim Jong-il's orders, all the mountain villages are now growing poppies,
the basic ingredient for producing opium and heroin.
The whole population is put to work.
You have whole towns whose entire economy is based on this production.
Where school-age children are taken to the fields to help with the harvest.
Even soldiers are often used as labor to help produce opium.
It was called the White Campanula farm.
We were stationed there in turn for three months to harvest poppy flowers.
I actually harvested poppies.
It was a big opium farm.
At the time, I didn't know that selling opium was illegal.
That's just the tip of the iceberg.
In fact, producing drugs is easy, especially when you control the police forces
and state authorities.
What's difficult is smuggling it abroad, bringing back the proceeds and
laundering them.
To move the merchandise and repatriate the dirty money, Bureau 39 coordinates
all the state services involved in drug trafficking.
At the time, the easiest way to distribute drugs was through the diplomatic corps.
A diplomat has immunity, which means that a foreign government has no right to
search him.
This also applies to their luggage. These suitcases are the property of the
North Korean state.
Little by little, in the 70s and 80s, North Korea's diplomatic network became
the regime's main channel for exporting drugs around the world and earning
foreign currency.
The profits are difficult to estimate, but must have been in the region of $40
million every 6 months.
If there were a university of organized crime, there would be books explaining
how the North Korean government does it.
Thanks to the opium and heroin trade, Kim Jong-il is becoming considerably
richer, enabling the regime to survive the crisis.
But above all, he prepared for his accession to power by buying off the
country's powerful families.
In 1976, for the party's 30th anniversary, 5,000 cadres received Japanese
refrigerators and luxury watches bearing Kim Il-sung's signature.
Everyone knew it was Kim Jong-il who was organizing all this. He was discreetly
reinforcing his status.
Kim Jong-il built his power alongside his father. Kim Il-sung let him do so, at
least in part, to ensure a smooth transition of power.
In the early 1980s, the two Kims held the country. While the son ran the mafia
organization, the father pursued his secret nuclear program.
In 15 years, the North Koreans have never succeeded in building a bomb using the
civilian reactor supplied by the Soviets.
But they have just found plans in British archives that should enable them to
build a new one, of a different design.
These plans were freely available. The North Koreans had managed to obtain all
the construction parameters.
The North Koreans have a very good reason for choosing this type of reactor,
because they have natural uranium. They have enormous uranium resources. They
don't need to import fuel from abroad.
This type of reactor can be used for both civil and military purposes, because
if you take the nuclear fuel out and process it, then you can potentially make a bomb.
This time, the North Koreans are going to move forward in disguise. In 1985,
under pressure from the Soviets, they agreed to sign the Nuclear
Non-Proliferation Treaty.
But on the Yongbyon site, they built the new reactor that would finally enable
them to have the bomb.
In the early 90s, the Soviet Union collapsed. The bipolar world inherited from
the Second World War disappeared, and North Korea lost its Soviet guardian.
Feeling isolated on the international stage, Kim Il-sung wanted to reassure the
world on the nuclear front.
He accepted a visit from inspectors from the IAEA, the International Atomic
Energy Agency set up by the United Nations to monitor nuclear non-proliferation.
Kim Il-sung knows full well that he is not complying with the treaty he has
signed, but he is convinced that his military installations are so well hidden
that the IAEA will not notice a thing.
In May 1992, an IAEA delegation visited North Korea's nuclear facilities for the
first time.
Heading the delegation was the Director of the international agency, Hans Blix,
who had come to see for himself whether the plant was indeed producing electricity.
The Yongbyon site is surrounded by concrete walls and iron gates.
The technology used on site is old but effective.
They have old equipment dating back to the 50s and 60s, in other words, to the
time when they acquired it.
But the reactor itself and the equipment to manufacture the nuclear material,
even if it would never pass safety standards, are highly functional.
The North Korean engineers are proud to present their nuclear technology.
They show Hans Blix the reactor core, which has been in operation for 6 years.
The tour continues to the cooling pool. Despite the dilapidated state of the
equipment, everything is in perfect working order.
At the end of his visit, Hans Blix can't get over it.
We're impressed by the engineers' ability to build their own
have managed to build their reactor all by themselves.
When the experts leave, the North Koreans are confident. They have succeeded in
concealing their military activity.
A clandestine waste reprocessing plant, of course, which they hid from the inspectors.
Before we received the inspectors in 1992, we had hidden all the nuclear equipment.
I was vice-president of the waste treatment plant.
We covered certain parts of the plant with lead sheets, because lead blocks
radioactivity, which would prevent the group of inspectors from measuring it.
But two months later, a new team of IAEA inspectors was sent to the site.
This time, to take samples and carry out precise analyses that the North Koreans
had not anticipated.
In 1992, we had new tools at the IAEA. This new verification method was based on
the collection of environmental samples.
Using absorbent cotton, we collected dust deposited on surfaces.
It contained minute particles of uranium and plutonium.
I think they were caught off guard because we were using these new investigative methods.
They didn't know about it. That's when the problems started.
And these analyses reveal that the North Koreans are secretly reprocessing their
nuclear waste. A totally forbidden practice.
If you have a reprocessing plant, it's a sign that you want plutonium. And why
do you need plutonium to make bombs? It was very alarming.
That's why we had no choice but to take it to the UN Security Council.
For Washington, these revelations are proof that the North Koreans do indeed
have a clandestine factory for military use.
The CIA had had doubts for years.
As early as 1986, satellite photos showed something resembling the foundations
of a reprocessing plant.
You could see trenches between sites that had no reason to be connected.
You could also see tanks that were to be used to store waste.
Washington set conditions.
The North Koreans would no longer be able to handle their nuclear waste without
the presence of IAEA agents.
If they removed this fuel to make plutonium, they would have had enough to build
6 bombs.
For us, this was a very serious problem.
We had already informed the North Koreans that if they started reprocessing this
fuel, in other words, recovering the plutonium, this would have serious consequences.
But the North Koreans did not heed these injunctions and continued the
clandestine reprocessing of their nuclear waste.
On the other hand, they decided to stop hiding. On the contrary, their nuclear
program will become their weapon of deterrence.
We threatened them with very heavy sanctions if they continued. They told us
that if we imposed sanctions, they would consider it an act of war.
Very explicit terms.
They threatened to turn Seoul into a sea of flames.
It was a very serious crisis.
It was my first issue as Secretary of Defense, the prospect of war.
The situation between the United States and North Korea was escalating rapidly.
It was getting out of control.
The North Koreans' provocations seemed to be leading them straight into a new
war with the United States.
It was then that former president Jimmy Carter offered his services to the White House.
He wanted to go to Pyongyang to try to open negotiations with the North Korean leaders.
We had no formal discussions, no embassy in Pyongyang.
No way to communicate directly.
So the President authorized Carter to go to Pyongyang to talk with Kim Il-sung.
President Clinton agreed to let Carter intervene.
But at the same time, he launched preparations for military intervention.
On June 15, Jimmy Carter and his wife arrived at the DMZ, the demilitarized zone
separating the two Koreas.
They crossed the border on foot, surrounded by secret service agents.
A delegation from Pyongyang had come to welcome them.
It was the first time an American president had set foot on North Korean soil.
These images of Carter crossing the DMZ, it's a proud feeling to be on an equal footing,
to have an American president come directly to North Korea.
The next day, Jimmy Carter met Kim Il-sung at the presidential palace.
The handshake was historic.
In Pyongyang, they ate meals together and visited the city and its monuments.
But Carter hadn't come to visit the country with the North Korean leaders.
What he wanted was to avoid war.
He was trying to use these moments of socialization to find a solution to the problem.
Carter complied with protocol, but he knew he didn't have much time to negotiate.
11,000 kilometers away, President Clinton is about to launch a military intervention.
Preparations have been underway at the White House since early this morning.
And intervention is imminent.
I was in the Situation Room briefing the President and the entire national
security team.
We had no way of assessing what Kim Il-sung had in mind,
but we thought there was a reasonable chance he would carry out these threats.
We really wanted President Carter to succeed in defusing the crisis.
But at the same time, we couldn't be sure of his success,
and we needed to take preventive measures.
So we had to be ready before imposing sanctions.
And I suggested sending an extra 30,000 troops to South Korea.
That would have been a very important and provocative maneuver.
There was also the option of destroying Yongbyon before it could produce atomic bombs.
We had a chance to stop their nuclear program before it began in earnest.
Because everything was right in front of our eyes at Yongbyon.
The reactor, the fuel rods, everything was there.
President Clinton hesitated.
Any military action would lead to retaliation by the North Koreans.
And the consequences would be dramatic.
The worry, of course, was that the North Koreans would use their artillery,
hidden in underground tunnels along the demilitarized zone,
to destroy Seoul, a city of over 11 million inhabitants.
This would have caused enormous damage.
General Locke estimated that a new Korean War would result in a million casualties,
and more than a billion dollars in material damage.
And this is where Jimmy Carter, in a way, fell from the sky.
Just as President Clinton was about to make his decision,
he received an urgent message.
Former President Carter is on the line.
We were in the process of presenting options to the president,
when a call came in from Pyongyang,
saying the North Koreans were ready to talk.
They knew we were meeting, and that it was the right time to get their message across.
There was no way the timing was a coincidence.
Our meeting had been going on for an hour, and the call came just then.
The president asked me to answer the call,
and so I went into a very small room, a sort of phone booth,
and had a conversation with former President Jimmy Carter.
He described to me what he thought he'd gotten.
Carter would have gotten Kim Il-sung to promise to stop reprocessing nuclear waste.
Apparently, all the North Koreans wanted,
was to open negotiations.
They felt they could negotiate a deal with the West, and even more so with the Americans.
The United States would become their sponsor, their protector.
There was a great deal of tension.
First, the meeting was interrupted by Pyongyang's appeal, then our conditions
stipulating that North Korea had to commit to stopping waste reprocessing before
the end of our discussion,
and the final answer was yes.
The Americans had approached the precipice.
They had foreseen the disaster that lay ahead if they went through with their logic.
And Jimmy Carter saved us from ourselves.
The meeting was adjourned because the idea of sending 30,000 troops to Seoul was
becoming obsolete.
Kim Il-sung has no intention of stopping his program.
But by making false promises to the Americans, he has bought himself some time.
On the other hand, he has another problem to deal with.
He has just realized that his son Kim Jong-il has been lying to him about the
country's economic situation.
Despite the various businesses he has set up over the past 20 years, the coffers
are empty.
The old patriarch, obsessed with his bomb, never saw it coming.
Kim Il-sung had decided to return to business.
And then he discovered that the North Korean economy was in meltdown.
He hadn't realized it until now.
Kim Il-sung realized that many factories were not operating normally.
There was also a problem with food distribution in the country.
It was no longer guaranteed.
Kim Il-sung was very disappointed and disillusioned.
Kim Il-sung dismissed all Kim Jong-il's men.
He took charge and wanted to receive all reports on North Korea directly.
From then on, the relationship between father and son deteriorated sharply.
That day, father and son had to talk on the phone.
And the conversation goes awry.
It is alleged that he had a fit of rage, that he cursed his son devilishly,
that he threatened to take away his power, and then that he lost his temper and
fell down.
At the age of 82, in the middle of an argument with his son, Kim Il-sung
collapsed from a heart attack.
He disappeared, dreadful. He's been around for 50 years.
It was an unimaginable tragedy for the population, who, deep down, had never
known anything like it before.
A few days later, the tribute paid to the dictator was the height of the regime.
For 10 hours, the funeral cortege marched 40 km in front of a huge crowd.
We learned about it from the media. At first, we couldn't believe it.
How can a god die? A god doesn't die.
The North Korean people were stunned.
So the top brass sent women to weep.
And when they started sobbing, people empathized.
We all became sad when we saw all those women in tears.
And we started crying too.
When we heard of his death, everyone was shocked.
I was upset, as if I'd lost my own father.
I cried for several days.
Kim Il-sung's body is embalmed.
It costs astronomical sums, we're talking about 10 million dollars, crazy things.
It's on display in the palace, which has been completely refurbished, with
absolutely extraordinary measures. You have to queue for hours to get in.
You have to go through cameras. And if you're completely decontaminated, no dust
can get in.
They tell you how to stand.
You can watch for half a minute, and then we pass Kim Il-sung's catafalque.
Kim Il-sung was like the sun for the people.
But when the sun suddenly disappeared, the world went dark.
North Koreans were completely disoriented.
Kim Il-sung died.
At the age of 52, his son, Kim Jong-il, could at last officially assume absolute power.
The North Korean population hadn't seen much of him.
They had only heard his voice for 12 seconds during a military parade in the
early 90s.
He was a kind of mysterious figure who took power.
Kim Jong-il, of course, makes it clear that from now on, he's in charge, and
he's in charge alone.
He is now the new Kim Il-sung.
With the death of Kim Il-sung, the international community began to wonder.
Will his successor, Kim Jong-il, have the same nuclear obsession? Or will he
respect the promise his father had made to Jimmy Carter a few months earlier?
After years of anti-American propaganda, nothing is less certain.
In any case, his priority at the moment is to find a way to revive his country,
which is in ruins.
In 1994, Kim Jong-il inherited a country he himself had brought to its knees.
During his years at the helm, he had enriched the country's top dignitaries and
the army.
But he had also considerably impoverished the population.
Everything collapsed the year he came to power.
Within months, the country was hit by an unprecedented famine.
If there had been markets, people could have survived.
But there weren't even any markets any more.
The state was the sole provider of food for the North Korean people.
They couldn't imagine the government starving them out.
So they waited for the food rations.
And they all starved to death waiting.
The abandoned children, the starving, it all happened at once.
Like war.
It didn't happen gradually.
It was a brutal change in people's daily lives.
People were thrown into a state of panic by it.
There were so many dead bodies.
People came to collect them and bury them.
In mountainous regions, meals were offered for this work.
They were called 827 carts.
In the summer of 1995, isolated and cornered,
Kim Jong-il decided to open his country to international aid for the first time.
He had no choice. He had to let in foreign NGOs to avoid the total collapse of
his regime.
One evening, we received a written message by fax,
telling us that the North Korean authorities were inviting us to work in their country.
We were obviously completely stunned.
This was the last thing we expected, given the North Korean regime's reputation
for absolute closure.
We knew that children were starving to death.
The question was raised.
Could we let children, innocent people, starve to death? We had a moral
obligation to intervene, whatever the regime.
North Korea is becoming the most assisted country in the world.
All the humanitarian organizations are there.
Aid worth billions of dollars.
These were huge budgets. The bulk was rice, of course.
Absolutely enormous quantities, capable of providing the regime with a very
clear crutch.
At that point, North Korea could have collapsed.
The pressure on the regime was incredible.
But they received outside help, and that undoubtedly saved them.
But while his country was dying, the dictator kept his family in opulence.
His children have grown up in the greatest secrecy.
Particularly his three sons, born of extramarital relationships.
The youngest, Kim Jong-un, is the child of his fourth mistress.
In the 90s, nobody knew Kim Jong-un, including those in power.
Nobody knew who he was, his name didn't exist.
Kim Jong-un was not allowed to meet anyone.
No one was supposed to know who his mother was.
Why not?
Because she wasn't the legitimate wife.
She couldn't appear.
No one was allowed to meet the hidden members of the Kim family.
The executives and family entourage didn't dare treat him like a child his own age.
They couldn't be familiar with him because he might be the next leader.
Kim Jong-un had a huge room full of toys, but no friends. When he went to
school, his teachers were terrified,
like in those movies where a child can kill you with a look.
Kim Jong-il realized that this was not healthy for a child.
So the dictator decided to send Kim Jong-un abroad to study,
in a country where secrets are closely guarded: Switzerland.
Switzerland is considered by many absolute monarchies to be the "nec plus
ultra", where you get a good education and don't get asked too many questions.
He wanted his children to live out their youth like everyone else,
let them have friends, because it's an age when politics are not yet discussed.
In 1995, Kim Jong-un was enrolled in a private college in Bern, under the name Pak-un.
He was to receive a normal education.
At the time, Kim Jong-un was very athletic, and spoke quite a bit of French and German,
He didn't see many people.
He was surrounded by 2-3 other very young-looking Koreans who pretended to be
students, when in fact they were bodyguards.
The kids thought he was the son of a diplomat.
He was very introverted and loyal to the few friends he had.
I think he really wanted to have a normal childhood, with normal relationships.
At the age of 14, Kim Jong-un seems happy to be away from the hassles of the palace,
because 8,000 kilometers away, his father finds himself embroiled in an
international scandal.
The dramatic situation in North Korea, faced with a terrible famine,
After Médecins du Monde, Médecins Sans Frontières announced its departure from
the country, demanding greater transparency from the authorities.
Some talk of 3 million victims in a country where information is very difficult
to verify.
In October 1998, several NGOs announced their departure from North Korea.
They accused the Pyongyang regime of diverting all humanitarian aid intended for
the population.
We decided to leave because we judged our own aid to be ineffective,
from the point of view of the people it was supposed to help. In other words,
the so-called sick in great distress, the so-called population groups in great distress,
we didn't really have access to them.
The resources sent by international organizations should have been distributed
to the people.
But in fact, it was the privileged class, the military and the police, who benefited.
By diverting humanitarian aid, Kim Jong-il was able to maintain his army and,
consequently, his regime.
But he did so at the cost of a famine that decimated more than 10% of his
population in three years.
The international community believed that the North Korean regime would collapse
with the fall of the Soviet Union
and that its nuclear program was under control thanks to the agreements signed
under Bill Clinton.
But the attacks in New York on September 11, 2001 changed everything.
The new American president, George W. Bush, placed North Korea on the axis of
evil alongside Iran and Syria,
countries likely to supply terrorists with weapons of mass destruction.
Above all, the American secret services were to discover that the Pyongyang
regime was doing just fine,
thanks to a most unexpected financing system.
On May 20, 2003, two high-ranking North Korean officials who had fled their
country testified before the US Senate.
With their faces masked, they revealed the most unspoken secrets of Kim
Jong-il's regime.
We're busy manufacturing and selling legal drugs to other countries to support
the regime from junkyard to cage.
to support a financially strangled regime.
North Korea must be the only regime in the world
to have set up a state-level drug trafficking business.
They were high-level defecators. They were clearing up important questions.
How can a small country like North Korea survive and continue its weapons program?
They tell of their own role in this organized government crime.
They explain the collusion between North Korea and foreign mafias.
U.S. senators are stunned to discover the existence of Bureau 39 and its
involvement in international drug trafficking.
Methamphetamines, synthetic drugs, have now replaced the heroin production of
the 80s.
Over the past 30 years, North Korean drug and contraband trafficking has taken
on unimaginable proportions.
It's worth billions, there's no doubt about it. Billions of dollars.
We don't talk about millions anymore, because you have to include revenues from
drugs, contraband, fake cigarettes and counterfeit bills.
70 to 80% of the currency collected by North Korea is illegitimate and illegal.
Comparing North Korea to the Italian Mafia is interesting, but it overlooks the
difference in scale.
The Italian mafia, even at its peak in the 70s and 80s, never reached the
sophistication, size and global reach of North Korean organized crime.
We were becoming aware that their weapons programs were being developed thanks
to the revenues from this kind of activity.
American investigations are also uncovering disturbing alliances.
In February 2004, Abdul Kader Khan, the father of the Pakistani atomic bomb, was
arrested by the Pakistani authorities.
He admitted having sold centrifuges to North Korea, the devices used to enrich
uranium to make bombs.
Abdul Kader Khan had helped the North Koreans to prepare.
First, he gave them a starter kit for two dozen centrifuges of two different
types in the late 1990s.
Then he taught them how to operate them.
They then managed to assemble all these parts and started building more
centrifuges themselves. The North Koreans are very, very good technically.
The program could be run in a room the size of my apartment.
The research and development didn't require any special facilities.
Faced with this damning information, the Bush administration decided to strike a blow.
If we wanted to stop North Korea's nuclear program, we had to block the money.
The Treasury realized that North Korea was using an offshore bank to manage its
illicit activities.
On September 25, 2005, the US Treasury designated Banco Delta Asia as an
accomplice in Pyongyang's money-laundering activities.
All North Korean assets were frozen.
When sanctions were imposed on the bank, the North Koreans started screaming
like never before.
It was clear that we had touched a sensitive point in their system, because
Banco Delta Asia was the main bank for their money transfers.
The other banks started thinking "if the US sanctions me, I'm going to be
associated with North Korea and that's not worth it".
So we were able to disconnect them from the international banking system.
But these economic sanctions will not weaken the North Koreans. Quite the
contrary, in fact.
On October 9, 2006, a communiqué from Pyongyang took the Americans by storm.
North Korea had just successfully carried out its first nuclear test.
It was only a partial success.
And the explosive power was weak, on the order of a fizzle.
But it was a shock.
One of the Bush administration's mistakes with North Korea was to let an
identified threat, sealed up and under camera surveillance, materialize in a few
years and become a functional nuclear bomb.
There are few events that change the way a country is perceived by others.
With the 2006 nuclear test, North Korea radically changed its status.
It's a demonstration of power.
They're showing that they're not going to let themselves be pushed around and
that they won't back down under pressure.
There was real concern about the reaction of the United States, because North
Korea had crossed a real red line with this first nuclear test.
And President Bush had just invaded Iraq and Afghanistan.
Indeed, the United States has other priorities.
Embroiled in several wars in the Middle East, George W. Bush does not want
another armed conflict.
He prefers to opt for negotiation.
Bush had been contemptuous of the North Koreans, and he really hated them.
But by 2005, he knew he'd made the wrong decisions in Afghanistan and Iraq.
And I think he also knew what a mistake he'd made with North Korea.
That's why he reacted to the nuclear tests by advocating a negotiated solution.
Kim Jong-il has succeeded. He now has nuclear weapons, and the international
community is very worried about him.
Attacking him would mean risking a retaliation and a terrible escalation for everyone.
But at 66, the dictator is not at his best. At the end of the 2000s, the
question of the regime's continuity once again arose.
Kim Jong-il was about to designate the person who would take over the dynasty.
Having survived a stroke in 2008, he didn't want to take any risks.
Kim Jong-il suffered from numerous health problems.
Heart, kidney, liver. He had high blood pressure and was overweight.
Like his father before him, he sought his successor among his children.
Logically, he could have chosen his eldest son, Kim Jong-nam.
But he has too bad a reputation.
He spends more time in China than in North Korea and doesn't seem to have the
soul of a dictator.
It doesn't fit because the character doesn't fit.
Kim Jong-nam doesn't like the army, it bores him.
For a militaristic regime, that's something that doesn't fit. He's too curious,
he travels abroad a lot.
He went to Shanghai, for example, and came back enthusiastic.
When Kim Jong-nam was still at the heart of the regime,
he was in favor of Chinese-style economic reforms.
And his father didn't like that.
And gradually, we see a break between father and son, albeit in fits and starts.
Kim Jong-il therefore chose another successor, his youngest son, Kim Jong-un,
who completed his studies in Switzerland.
On October 10, 2010, during the party's 65th anniversary,
Kim Jong-un made his first official appearance alongside his father.
He has just completed military training and possesses an undeniable asset,
he bears a striking resemblance to his founding father, Kim Il-sung.
Kim Jong-un is the spitting image of his grandfather.
He's tall like him, massive like him, and he loves the army.
He's in the army all the time, wearing a fur coat, he loves to work out, he does
exercises with soldiers. He's extraordinarily popular, a true military man at heart.
Kim Jong-un is the spitting image of his grandfather.
He's strong-willed, determined and has a big ego.
It's like in the Hollywood film The Godfather.
Marlon Brando has 3 sons.
The first is a heavy drinker and a womanizer. The second is a little weak.
And the third is exactly like his father.
From that day on, Kim Jong-un's rise was to be meteoric.
No one had foreseen Kim Jong-un's appearance.
That's why the world's media and experts were surprised.
He was the son of Kim Jong-il's mistress.
I thought it was really disgusting.
It didn't make sense.
How could a country with such a hereditary system exist? I was shocked.
For the succession to take place smoothly, the regime is going to display all
its power.
In particular, its nuclear power.
One month after this ceremony,
two of the world's leading nuclear specialists were invited to North Korea.
The first is Siegfried Hecker,
former director of an American nuclear weapons research laboratory.
The second is Robert Carlin.
He is a former CIA agent. These two independent experts will visit Yongbyon,
North Korea's most secret nuclear site.
They led us into a large building.
In a control room,
there were several technicians in white with computers.
They took us to a window, and there we were speechless.
My mouth must have been hanging open.
I couldn't believe my eyes.
In front of us were around 2,000 centrifuges, by a rough estimate.
It was a brand-new installation.
They wanted us to see it.
That was the purpose of our visit. They wanted the Americans to know.
The two men are clearly stunned.
The sight of these centrifuges,
opens up terrifying perspectives on North Korea's nuclear capabilities.
How many centrifuges do they have?
How much uranium can they really manufacture? And the answer is "we don't know".
By my reckoning,
they have enough plutonium and enriched uranium to make 20 to 25 bombs.
And they have the capacity to make a bomb,
every 6 to 7 weeks.
A new atomic bomb,
every 6 weeks.
The conclusion is that international sanctions have had no effect.
The building housing the centrifuges had been under constant surveillance for years.
And no intelligence service, as far as I know,
saw a single centrifuge arrive in that building. Does this mean that our
intelligence services are no good?
No, it just means that you can't track a centrifuge.
It's just too easy to hide.
As for the political message, it's unambiguous.
Kim Jong-un, the third in line,
will not stop the nuclear program initiated by his father and grandfather.
The North Koreans wanted to be ready to be in a position of strength when the
heir came to power.
They needed to be as strong as possible during this period when the outside
world perceived them as weak and vulnerable.
Kim Jong-il died of a heart attack in December 2011.
History repeats itself.
As soon as the funeral took place, his successor, Kim Jong-un, took center stage.
He accompanied the body of the deceased dictator,
before a crowd in collective hysteria.
The young Kim Jong-un is seen walking bareheaded,
braving the cold in front of the catafalque.
We see the entire Korean people braving the cold.
From the moment the heir, young Kim Jong-un,
walked alone in front of the coffin, bareheaded,
the people had to do the same.
That day, a handful of men accompanied the heir around the funeral vehicle.
This was the regency team set up by Kim Jong-il to supervise his son during his
first years in power.
Unlike his father,
who had been in the party apparatus since 1964,
30 years before inheriting power,
Kim Jong-un had very little time to learn how to manipulate the various echelons
of power.
Kim Jong-il therefore created a kind of network around himself to ensure his
son's survival.
Behind the heir, the man in the black coat,
is General Jang Song-taek.
It's his uncle, one of the regime's most powerful men.
He was supposed to bring all his knowledge of defense and military matters to
Kim Jong-un.
Jang Song-thaek is the regent who oversees the economy and relations with China.
He also explains policy to Kim Jong-un.
The question on everyone's lips is, what will be the attitude of this new North
Korean monarch?
Kim Jong-un's Swiss education raised a lot of hopes in the United States and the
rest of the world.
Many thought it would make him more open to reform.
We didn't know anything about him, but since he had lived abroad,
maybe he would change his business model.
And from his very first public appearances, Kim Jong-un has been sending out
signs of change,
like the presence of his wife by his side.
We said, "There, just like elsewhere, just like in the West, just like in the
United States, there's a first lady."
That day, the couple came to see a show inspired by Walt Disney characters,
an American symbol previously banned in Pyongyang.
It's a bit childish, it's not very sophisticated, Minnie, Donald, etc., dancing.
Still, it's quite a step for a regime that has tended to make Manichean accusations
in relation to this American junk culture.
He tried to send a message.
If you recognize me as the leader of a nuclear power,
then I'm ready to make concessions.
If you guarantee the survival and security of my regime,
I won't behave like my father.
But beneath his harmless exterior, Kim Jong-un hides another face,
that of a dictator even more violent and radical than his predecessors.
On December 8th, 2013, in the middle of a party meeting,
to everyone's surprise, Kim Jong-un ordered the immediate arrest of his uncle,
Jang Song-thaek, the mentor chosen for him by his father.
Jang controlled the money from foreign trade.
And when Kim Jong-un needed these funds, he had to go through him.
Kim Jong-un didn't have absolute power, and that enraged him.
To oust this uncle, who had taken on too much power,
Kim Jong-un accused him of treason, corruption and promiscuity.
A public humiliation that doesn't stop there.
Having someone of Jang Song-taek's stature,
walk out of a political bureau meeting in front of the entire leadership team,
and in front of the whole world,
and then exhibited at the trial, with bruises on his face, sends a very strong
message to the regime's cadres.
The message is that there is only one leader, and that leader is Kim Jong-un.
After a summary trial, Jang Song-taek was executed.
Such violence shocked everyone, including those in North Korea.
I couldn't imagine Kim killing his uncle like that.
It was shocking.
Because in North Korea, members of the Kim family didn't kill each other.
Of course, there have always been executions of high-ranking officials,
but that was behind the curtain.
Never like this, in public.
We knew this was just the beginning,
that even more frightening events were to come.
In the months that followed, Kim Jong-un ruthlessly eliminated all high-ranking
Korean dignitaries and party cadres likely to overshadow him.
An unprecedented purge that began to worry his powerful neighbor China.
Until then, China had always supported the Kim regime.
North Korea serves as a bulwark against the American presence in South Korea.
But Kim Jong-un is proving to be uncontrollable,
Beijing reportedly considered removing him from power.
China was in favor of regime change in North Korea.
A surgical operation to replace Kim Jong-un,
which would suit both the United States and South Korea.
One of the potential replacements could be Kim Jong-nam, his elder brother.
The one their father did not want as successor.
He has been living under Chinese protection for several years.
That day, he was at Kuala Lumpur airport, returning from a trip to Malaysia.
A year earlier, political refugees in exile had asked Kim Jong-nam to become the
head of a dissident government.
He refused.
The North Korean government immediately ordered him to return.
Once again, Kim Jong-nam refused.
Kim Jong-nam has the ideal profile, both close to Beijing and a member of the
North Korean dynasty.
His appointment would allow China to take control without destabilizing the regime.
But he will never return from his trip to Malaysia.
We see Kim Jong-nam, a businessman, walking quietly, unescorted, without a bodyguard,
only to be abruptly joined by two women who place their hands on his face before disappearing.
The scene, filmed by airport cameras, lasted just a few seconds.
After spraying him in the face with liquid, the 2 women melt into the crowd.
Kim Jong-nam, taken aback, did not react.
But a few minutes later, he collapsed and fainted.
It was soon learned that he had been out of breath and had gone to the clinic,
where he died shortly afterwards.
So the assassination was staged in spectacular fashion, and it's all very mysterious.
The sophistication of the operation, the acquisition of equipment, the modus
operandi and the extent of the network required are all clues pointing to the
involvement of a state.
Malaysian authorities found traces of a powerful nerve agent on the victim's face.
The North Koreans deny any involvement in the assassination.
But the method used makes them the main suspects.
The North Korean government has a very long history of very, very daring
intelligence operations.
They have commandos specialized in targeted assassinations.
They are among the best in the world.
The message behind this assassination is guys, you're going to have to deal with
me one way or another.
In just a few years, Kim Jong-un has eliminated all those who could threaten his
power within the country.
And to earn the respect of the international community, he's banking on his
nuclear power.
He's going to make a spectacle of it.
Every missile launch, every atomic bomb test will be staged to arouse fear.
Under Kim Jong-un, there is a tendency to harden positions.
Permanent demonstrations of force that get more extreme every time.
He's spiraling further and further out of control.
The number of tests, both ballistic and nuclear, under the young leader's reign
has doubled or tripled.
Nuclear and missile tests are also there to show that the regime will survive,
and that it's in everyone's interest to accept it.
We're at a critical juncture where nothing seems to stop the North Koreans'
determination to develop the capacity to strike us.
This presents the United States with some very difficult choices.
In July 2017, Kim Jong-un witnessed the launch of a new intercontinental missile.
The young dictator had just fulfilled his grandfather's dream of putting the
United States within firing range.
A reasonable projection is estimated at around 10,000 kilometers.
In other words, part of the US territory is already accessible, the West Coast
and perhaps the East Coast too.
It remains to be seen whether North Korea has already achieved, or is about to
achieve, the Grail, the ultimate goal,
i.e. to place an operational nuclear weapon on a ballistic missile that can have
an intercontinental range, reaching as far as the USA.
Have they already achieved this goal? It's not certain, but what is certain is
that they're not far off.
The United States is now within theoretical range of North Korean missiles.
A situation that has the new American president, Donald Trump, in a tizzy.
He reacts violently to every provocation from Kim Jong-un.
North Korea had better stop threatening the United States,
or it will face fire and fury on a scale the world has never seen before.
There's only one person in the world today who's more unpredictable than Kim
Jong-un, and that's Donald Trump.
There's no way of predicting what might happen.
The risk of an uncontrolled escalation or a poorly managed incident is even
greater today between North Korea and the United States than it was during the
Cold War between Moscow and Washington.
North Korea specialists are at their wits' end.
The situation has deteriorated to such an extent that disaster seems inevitable.
We no longer know what to do with North Korea. Everything has been tried.
The moment of truth is approaching.
A conventional war would be devastating. But if there is a nuclear escalation,
the consequences will be unimaginable.